# Fanchi Meng

Email fanchi@ualberta.ca
Portfolio https://fanchi.github.io
Lab http://biomine.cs.vcu.edu

Phone 780-802-6821

## **Background**

I am a PhD graduate specifying in Software Engineering and Intelligent Systems at the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Alberta. I have experience in Java, Python, machine learning, deep learning and (big) data analysis.

#### **Education**

2014/01 - 2018/01	PhD in Software Engineering and Intelligent Systems, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada.
2006/09 - 2013/06	Bachelor and Master in Computer Science and Technology, College of Information Engineering, Northwest Agriculture and Forestry University (project "985" top university), Xi'an, China.

## **Experience**

2014/01 – 2018/01 Research assistant at University of Alberta. Responsible for:

- Developing and deploying machine learning based methods to predict functions from biology data.
- Retrieving and analyzing data from databases and searching for patterns between these data and some diseases.

2010/06 – 2010/10 Intern software developer at digital multimedia retrieval lab, Northwest Agriculture and Forestry University. Responsible for developing windows client for a video conference system.

### **Representative Projects**

- 1. [Machine Learning] DMRpred
  - A machine learning model that predicts multi-functional regions from protein data (tabular data)
  - Binary classification
  - Machine learning model: Random Forest
  - Webserver: <a href="http://biomine.cs.vcu.edu/servers/DMRpred">http://biomine.cs.vcu.edu/servers/DMRpred</a>
  - Back end implementation: Java + MySQL
- 2. [Deep Learning] Plant seedling classification
  - Determine a plant's species from a photo
  - Multiclass classification
  - Machine learning model: Convolutional Neural Network
  - Framework: Keras with tensorflow backend
- 3. [Big Data] Recommender system
  - Movie recommender system running on Hadoop
  - Based on item-item collaborative filtering (item CF)
  - Five chained MapReduce jobs
  - Project page: <a href="https://github.com/fanchi/RecommenderItemCF">https://github.com/fanchi/RecommenderItemCF</a>

## **Representative Publications**

- 1. F. Meng, C. Wang and L. Kurgan, "fDETECT webserver: fast predictor of propensity for protein production, purification, and crystallization", *BMC Bioinformatics*, 18:580, 2017.
- 2. F. Meng and L. Kurgan, "DFLpred: High-throughput prediction of disordered flexible linker regions in protein sequences", *Bioinformatics*, vol. 32, pp. i341-i350, 2016.
- 3. F. Meng, C. Cai, and H. Yan, "A Bicluster-Based Bayesian Principal Component Analysis Method for Microarray Missing Value Estimation", *IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics*, vol. 18, pp. 863-871, 2014.

A full list of my projects and publications can be found at https://fanchi.github.io

## Skills

- Strong computer science fundamentals in data structures and algorithms.
- **Programming languages:** Python, Java and Matlab.
- Machine learning/data mining frameworks: scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Keras and Weka.
- **Big data:** Hadoop Map-Reduce.
- Database: SQL.
- Operating System: Linux shell/GUI.
- Version control/workflow: Git.